A Finding Aid to the Carus Gallery Records, 1967-2002, in the Archives of American Art AAA.carugall
Archives of American Art
Carus Gallery records
1967-2002
AAA.carugall
Archives of American Art
3.2 Linear feet
The records of Carus Gallery measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1967-2002. This collection documents Dorothea Carus Isserstedt's management of the New York gallery through a small amount of business and personal correspondence; business records regarding acquisitions, sales, and consignments; intentories of artwork and rare books; exhibition catalogs, press clippings, and other printed material; and photographs depicting artwork and exhibition installations.
Carus Gallery.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1974-2000 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Business Records, 1971-1996 (1.8 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Inventories, 1973-2002 (0.6 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1967-1992 (0.6 linear feet; Box 3-4)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1980s-1990s (4 folders; Box 4)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The records were donated to the Archives in 2004 by Dr. Gheorghe Costinescu and Mrs. Silvelin von Scanzoni Costinescu, the heirs and executors of Dorothy Carus Isserstedt’s estate.
Scope and Contents note
The records of Carus Gallery measure 3.2 linear feet and date from 1967-2002. This collection documents Dorothea Carus Isserstedt's management of the New York gallery through a small amount of business and personal correspondence; business records regarding acquisitions, sales, and consignments; intentories of artwork and rare books; exhibition catalogs, press clippings, and other printed material; and photographs depicting artwork and exhibition installations.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
The Carus Gallery was founded by Dorothea Carus Isserstedt (1914-2002). The gallery's primary interest was in European Graphic Arts, specifically German Expressionism, and Russian Constructivism. The gallery exhibited works by Alexander Archipenko, Ernst Barlach, Max Beckmann, Heinrich Campendonk, Otto Dix, Lyonel Feininger, Natalia Goncharova, George Grosz, Erich Heckel, Alexej Jawlensky, Wassily Kandinsky, Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Paul Klee, Gustav Klimt, Max Klinger, Kathe Kollowitz, El Lissitzky, Kazimir Malevich, László Moholy-Nagy, Marlow Moss, Otto Mueller, Edvard Munch, Emil Nolde, Christian Rohlfs and Egon Schiele.
In 1968, following the death of her parents, Isserstedt opened the Carus Gallery, which was located on the ground level of her home at 243 E 82nd street in New York. The gallery was relocated to Madison Avenue in 1974 and finally to 1044 Madison Avenue where it remained until Isserstedt's retirement in 1996.
Dorothy was born in 1914 in Elberfeld, Germany. She studied art history and archeology at Freiburg University, receiving a doctorate in 1944. Towards the end of World War II Dorothy escaped to East Germany where she settled in Hamburg and found work as a supervisor with the British Forces Network. In 1952 she immigrated to Yorkville, NY where she worked in her father's print and framing shop. Dorothy became an American citizen in 1957.
Carus Isserstedt, Dorthea, 1914-2002; Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York; Art, Modern--20th century; Constructivism (Art)--Russia; Expressionism (Art)--Germany; Futurism (Art)--Italy; Futurism (Art)--Russia; Photographs
- Correspondence, 1972-2000; Series 1; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence is minimal and consist primarily of art inquiries and similar letters to private collectors, conservators, and other galleries, specifically the Prakapas Gallery and the Skulima Galarie. There is also a small amount of correspondence regarding exhibitions and sales.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence, 1977-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Business Correspondence, Prakapas Gallery, 1974-1976; 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business Correspondence, Skulima Galerie, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Business Records, 1971-1996; Series 2; 1.8 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Business records include documents detailing acquisitions, sales, and consignments. Also found are financial, legal, and office documents.
  - Aquisitions and Sales, 1987-1990; 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Acquisitions, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sales, 1974-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
  - Invoices, 1971-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14-18)
  - Consignments, 1976-1996 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Pricelists, 1975-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Check Ledger, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Taxes, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Phone Log, 1988-1995 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - "Jawlensky Affair" Legal Proceedings, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Europe, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Notebooks, 1972-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- Inventories, 1973-2002; Series 3; 0.6 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Inventories include lists of artworks and rare books that could be found at the Carus Gallery. This series also includes a set of index cards containing catalog information regarding artwork.
  - Artworks, 1973-2002 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Rare Artists' Book Sale, 1967-1995 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Artists' Books and Prints, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Index Cards of Gallery Library, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Index Cards of Gallery Library, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Printed Material, 1967-1992; Series 4; 0.6 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Printed material includes a number of gallery catalogs, exhibition announcements, and press releases. The series also includes a catalog that was originally bound detailing information regarding the gallery's art holdings; most entries also include a small thumbnail. Additionally, this series contains a limited number of magazine and newspaper clippings.
  - Catalogs, 1975-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Gallery Invitations, 1975-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Catalog Clippings, A-J, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Catalog Clippings, K-Z, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Printed Artwork, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Carus Gallery Advertisements, 1967-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Press Kit Materials, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Photographic Material, 1980s-1990s; Series 5; 4 Folders Box 4
  Photographs and slides depict artwork by Felix Del Marle, El Lissitzky, and others. In addition to photographs, this series also contains slides of gallery installations at the Carus Gallery.
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Felix Del Marle, 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Artwork, El Lissitzky, 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Installation Photographs and Slides, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 8)